# Ragav Venkatesan

This document has embedded web-links and is made for a computer viewing only. Click here for a printable version.

CONTACT Email: ragav.venkatesan@gmail.com

Links LinkedIn Homepage Google Scholar GitHub Amazon Books

Summary

Senior Software Engineer with industry-leading experience in building enterprise-level, cost-efficient distributed machine learning and computer vision platforms and a breadth of research areas spanning from infrastructure such as MLops, data governance and management, inference APIs to cutting-edge techniques such as generative AI, object detection, semantic-segmentation, domain adaptation. video-enhancement, generative animation, multiple-instance learning, and neural-network compression.

Professional Experience

## (E1) NVIDIA

(N1) Senior Software Engineer - Maxine and Broadcast

August 2021 – Present

- Maxine NVIDIA Inference Microservices (NIMs) and APIs.
- AI-based video-enhancement features (webcam-denoising, artifact-reduction).
- Generative AI-based image animation (eye-contact, live-portrait) models.
- $\bullet$  Migrated Maxine and Broadcast workloads to Maglev .
- (E2) Amazon
  - (A1) Applied Scientist Amazon Alexa AI November 2019 August 2021
  - (A2) Applied Scientist Amazon Web Services, AI Labs Ma

May 2019 – November 2019

(A3) Research Scientist - Amazon Web Services, Sagemaker

November 2017 - May 2019

- Migrated Alexa AI workloads to AWS sagemaker platform.
- Shipped ENAS for Alexa voice training.
- Open source launch of Amazon SageMaker Reinforcement Learning.
- Launched Amazon SageMaker Object Detection Algorithms.
- Launched Amazon SageMaker Semantic Segmentation Algorithms.
- Launched Bring your own Tensorflow and MXNet models to SageMaker.
- Open source launched Neural Network Compression using AWS SageMaker RL.

(E3) Research Assistant - Arizona State University.

August 2011 – October 2017

 $\bullet\,$  The Diabetic Retinopathy project

Funding Agency: National Institutes of Health.

• The MIDAS project

Funding Agency: National Science Foundation.

(E4) Researcher Intern - Intel

December 2013 – August 2014

• Built vehicle and lane detection for automated driver assistance systems applications.

Education Doctor of Philosophy - Computer Science

October 2017

Advisor: Professor Baoxin Li

Arizona State University, Tempe, Arizona, USA

Master of Science - Electrical Engineering

August 2012

Advisor: Professor David Frakes

Arizona State University, Tempe, Arizona, USA

Bachelor of Engineering - Electronics and Communication Engineering

Anna University Channai Tamil Nadu India

June 2010

Anna University, Chennai, Tamil Nadu, India

(B1) Ragav Venkatesan, Baoxin Li, "Convolutional Neural Networks in Visual Computing: A Concise Guide", CRC Press, a Tyler & Francis company, 2017.

Ragav Venkatesan, Baoxin Li, "卷积神经网络与视觉计算", 机械工业出版社, 2019.

Воокѕ

- BOOK CHAPTERS (Bc1) Xiang Xu, Xiong Zhou, Ragav Venkatesan, Gurumurthy Swaminathan, Orchid Majumdar, " d-SNE: Domain Adaptation using Stochastic Neighborhood Embedding. " in Domain Adaptation in Computer Vision With Deep Learning, edited by Hemanth Venkateswara, Sethuraman Panchanathan, in Springer Nature, 2020.
  - (Bc2) Parag Chandakkar, Ragav Venkatesan, Baoxin Li, "Feature Extraction and Learning for Visual Data" in "Feature Engineering for Machine Learning and Data Analytics, CRC Press, a Tyler & Francis company, 2017.

Selected Peer-Reviewed Conferences

- (C1) Ansel MacLaughlin, Jwala Dhamala, Anoop Kumar, Sriram Venkatapathy, Ragay Venkatesan, Rahul Gupta, "Evaluating the Effectiveness of Efficient Neural Architecture Search for Sentence-Pair Tasks. ", in Workshop on Insights from Negative Results in NLP at the Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP), 2020. [ORAL]
- (C2) Xiang Xu, Xiong Zhou, Ragav Venkatesan, Gurumurthy Swaminathan, Orchid Majumdar " d-SNE: Domain Adaptation using Stochastic Neighborhood Embedding.", in IEEE International Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR), Long Beach, California, USA, 2019. [ORAL]
- (C3) Ragav Venkatesan, Jaya Vijetha Gattupalli, Baoxin Li, "On the generality of neural image features. ", in IEEE International Conference on Image Processing (ICIP), Phoenix, Arizona, USA, 2016. [ORAL]
- (C4) Ragav Venkatesan, Parag Shridhar Chandakkar, Baoxin Li, "Simpler non-parametric methods provide as good or better results to multiple-instance learning.", in IEEE International Conference on Computer Vision (ICCV), Santiago, Chile 2015. [Spotlight]
- (C5) Ragav Venkatesan, Parag Shridhar Chandakkar, Baoxin Li, "Video-Based Self-Positioning for Intelligent Transport Systems Applications", in the Tenth International Symposium on Visual Computing (ISVC), Las Vegas, Nevada, USA, 2015. [ORAL]
- (C6) Ragav Venkatesan, Christine Zwart, David Frakes, Baoxin Li, "Perception-Inspired Spatio-Temporal Video Deinterlacing", in the Eighth International Workshop on Video Processing and Quality Metrics for Consumer Electronics (VPQM), Tempe, Arizona, USA, 2014. [ORAL]
- (C7) Parag Shridhar Chandakkar\*, Ragav Venkatesan\*, Baoxin Li, Helen Li, "Retrieving clinically relevant diabetic retinopathy images using a multi-class multiple-instance framework." in proceedings of SPIE conference on Medical Imaging, International Society of Opticals and Photonics, Orlando, Florida, USA, 2013. [ORAL]
- (C8) Ragav Venkatesan\*, Parag Shridhar Chandakkar\*, Baoxin Li, Helen Li, "Classification of Diabetic Retinopathy Images Using Multi-Class Multiple-Instance Learning Based on Color Correlogram Features", in Proceedings of International Conference of the IEEE Engineering in Medicine and Biology Society 2012 (EMBC'12), San Diego, California, USA, 2012. [Poster]
- (C9) Ragav Venkatesan\*, Parag Shridhar Chandakkar\*, Baoxin Li, Helen Li, "Clinically Relevant Diabetic Retinopathy Image Retrieval Using a Multi-Class Multiple Instance Framework", in proceedings of ACM conference on Bio-informatics, Computational Biology and Biomedicine (ACM-BCB'12). Orlando, Florida 2012. [ORAL]
- (C10) Ragav Venkatesan, Christine Zwart, David Frakes, "Video Deinterlacing with Control Grid Interpolation Frameworks", in Proceedings of the IEEE International Conference on Image Processing (ICIP), Orlando, Florida, USA, 2012. [Poster] \* - Equal contribution from authors.

Selected Peer-Reviewed Journals

- (J1) Parag Shridhar Chandakkar, Ragav Venkatesan, Baoxin Li, "MIRank-KNN: Multiple Instance Retrieval of Clinically-Relevant Diabetic Retinopathy Image", in SPIE Journal of Medical Imaging, 2017.
- (J2) Ragav Venkatesan, Christine Zwart, David Frakes, Baoxin Li "Spatio-temporal Video Deinterlacing using Control Grid Interpolation", in SPIE Journal of Electronic Imaging, 24(2),
- (J3) Christine Zwart, Ragav Venkatesan, David Frakes, "Decomposed Multidimensional Control Grid Interpolation for Common Interpolation-Based Image Processing Applications in Consumer Electronics", in SPIE Journal of Electronic Imaging, vol. 24, no.4, pp.43012-1 to 43012-12. 2012.

## SELECTED ARXIV AND LONGFORM

- (A1) Ragav Venkatesan, Gurumurthy Swaminathan, Xiong Zhou, Anna Luo, "Out-of-the-box channel pruned networks.", arXiv: 2004.14584 2020.
- (A2) Ragav Venkatesan, Hemanth Venkateshwara, Sethuraman Panchanathan, Baoxin Li., "A strategy for an uncompromising incremental learner.", arXiv: 1705.00744 2017.
- (A3) Ragav Venkatesan, Vijetha Gattupalli, Baoxin Li., "Neural Dataset Generality.", arXiv: 1605.04369 2016.
- (A4) Ragav Venkatesan, Baoxin Li., "Diving deeper into mentee networks.", arXiv: 1604.08220 2016.
- (A5) Lydia Manikonda, **Ragav Venkatesan**, Subbarao Kambhampati, and Baoxin Li., "Evolution of fashion brands on Twitter and Instagram.", arXiv: 1512.01174 2015.

### DISSERTATION

- (R1) **Doctoral dissertation** Novel image features and learning techniques. October 2017
- (R2) Masters thesis Video Deinterlacing using Control Grid Interpolation Frameworks. August 2012
- (R3) Undergraduate thesis A comparative study of detection of faults and estimation of distance to faults on wired communication channels, using TDR and FDR techniques. May 2010

#### Issued Patents

- (P1) Ragav Venkatesan, Gurumurthy Swaminathan, Vineet Khare, Bharathan Balaji, Saurabh Gupta, Leo Parker Dirac, Sahika Genc" Decoupled machine learning training." US11861490B1
- (P2) Ragav Venkatesan, Gurumurthy Swaminathan, Xiong Zhou, Anna Luo, Vineet Khare" Applying compression profiles across similar neural network architectures." US11809992B1
- (P3) Ragav Venkatesan, Gurumurthy Swaminathan, Xiong Zhou, Anna Luo, Vineet Khare" Searching compression profiles for trained neural networks." US11755603B1
- (P4) Ragav Venkatesan, Gurumurthy Swaminathan, Xiong Zhou, Anna Luo, Vineet Khare "Reinforcement learning for training compression policies for machine learning models." US11501173B1
- (P5) Ragav Venkatesan, Gurumurthy Swaminathan, "Domain mapping for privacy preservation." US10567334B1

## TEACHING EXPERIENCE

- (T1) Instructor Amazon Machine Learning University. Convolutional Neural Networks (2018 - 2019)
- (T2) Instructor Arizona State University. CSE 591: Introduction to deep learning for visual computing (January - May 2017)
- (T3) Co-instructor Arizona State University. CSE 509: Digital Video Processing (August 2015 - December 2015)
- (T4) Teaching Assistant Arizona State University.
  - CSE 575: Statistical Machine Learning
    - Dr. Jingrui He (January 2015 May 2015)
  - CSE 569: Fundamentals of Statistical Learning
    - Dr. Baoxin Li (August 2014 December 2014 and August 2016 December 2016)
  - CSE 509: Digital Video Processing
    - Dr. David Claveau (August 2012 December 2012)
    - Dr. Hari Sundaram (August 2013 December 2013)
  - CSE 424, 485 and 486: Capstone Projects (January 2013 May 2013)
- (T5) Guest Lectures Arizona State University.

Duties in this position involve providing specific lectures in courses on invitation.

- CSE 569: Hidden Markov Models (September 2017)
- CSE 569: Neural Networks (October November 2017)

References

Will be provided on request.